Welcome to Radio Who, what, why. I'm
Jeff Shman. I think it's safe to say
that every institution of government
today is in chaos. Departments are
understaffed. The State Department is
hollowed out. Cabinet secretaries are
either apologizing for themselves or the
president, or they're traveling the
world trying to reassure allies and
adversaries. But few government
institutions are in the kind of direct
conflict, almost open hostility with the
administration as the intelligence
community and the CIA. From his botched
initial visit to Langley to 6 a.m.
tweets, not since Kennedy have we had a
president in open warfare with the
intelligence community. Here to talk
about all of this and a lot more, I'm
joined by my guest, John Keryaku. John
Keryako was a 15-year CIA veteran. He
rose through the ranks to the very
highest levels of the agency. He became
the first in the intelligence community
to expose the CIA's use of torture and
as a result he became one of the very
few Americans ever prosecuted under the
Espionage Act. He was considered a
whistleblower and served 23 months in
federal prison. He's the author of three
books. His latest out later this year is
Doing Time Like a Spy. It is my pleasure
to welcome John Keryaku to the program.
John, thanks so much for joining us.
Thank you so much for having me. The
pleasure is all mine. tell our listeners
a little bit about your history, your
background, and and in doing that, talk
a little bit about the way the CIA
changed and evolved during your 15 years
there. Sure. I spent the first half of
my career um as an analyst at the CIA,
working on the Middle East, specifically
on Iraq. I did that for about seven and
a half years, and then I made a very
unusual switch to counterterrorism
operations. I spoke Arabic and I spoke
Greek and u wanted to serve overseas. So
I changed to counterterrorism in uh in
1997. Uh finally felt like I knew what I
was doing around the time that 9/11 took
place and uh went to Pakistan as the
chief of counterterrorism operations for
the CIA there. The big change in those
years though, and it's something that I
naively believed would be temporary, was
a transition that we saw beginning on
9/11 away from a traditional spy agency
where CIA officers recruit spies to
steal secrets to what really has become
a paramilitary agency and even a cyber
military agency. Uh, the CIA is is
nothing like what it was when I joined
in early 1990. And I fear that uh that
it's changed forever. And how did those
changes I want to talk more about what
happened to you, but talk on the CIA.
How did those changes come about? It's
was was it like the frog in the boiling
water? Talk a little bit about that. It
was it was indeed like the frog in the
boiling water. Uh on on September 11th,
I was working in the CIA's
counterterrorism center and the
counterterrorism center had a certain
budget, right? Let's just say the budget
was
X. 3 days later, Congress voted an
appropriation
uh a special appropriation to augment
the counterterrorism c center's budget.
That was an addition of
160% of C of the CTC budget. So all of a
sudden there was more money in
counterterrorism than anybody could
possibly spend. Well, the CIA by its
very nature pushes the boundaries of
what it's allowed to do and it just
keeps pushing until the congressional
oversight committees tell it to stop.
Well, now flushed with cash, that's
exactly what they did. And nobody told
them to stop. Congress had passed the
Patriot Act. There were covert action
programs taking place. Uh, and all
anybody had to say was 9/11 and the CIA
got what it wanted. So, here we are now
16 years later, almost 16 years after
September 11th, and still nobody has
said stop to the CIA. That's how we've
found ourselves in this predicament. In
the immediate aftermath of 9/11, the CIA
was very involved in the actions in
Afghanistan. That was in and of itself a
kind of paramilitary operation. Talk
about the training that went into that
and obviously that kind of activity and
the planning for it begun even before
9/11. Well, see, that's really the
issue. Uh, at least from those early
days, there was almost no training. Uh,
on September 11th, like everybody else
in the building, I volunteered to go to
Afghanistan to do what I didn't even
really think it through, but I figured
my Arabic was fluent. I could at the
very least serve as a translator, maybe
work to to recruit some sources inside
al-Qaeda. Um, and I was denied. And I
was denied a second time and a third
time. And finally, I ran into a a
colleague in the hall uh whom I hadn't
seen in several months uh since the 9/11
attacks. And I said, "Hey, Billy, where
you been?" And he kind of whispers and
says, "I've been in Afghanistan." And I
said, "What are you doing in
Afghanistan?" And he looked at me like I
was crazy. And he said, "I've been
killing people. What do you think I've
been doing?" And I thought, "Well,
that's why they haven't sent me to
Afghanistan. They don't need
translators. They don't need recruiters.
they're just killing people. And I
realized then, this was in October of of
2001, I realized then that the entire
mission was changing. Now, if the if the
original mission was to destroy
al-Qaeda, we certainly succeeded in
doing that by the middle to the end of
2002, but the mission became muddled.
And that was really on the White House.
The mission became something akin to
nation building. And then all of a
sudden we realize that we have a problem
with the Taliban or we had a problem
with Hecmatiar or we didn't like
somebody else in the area. And here we
are now as I said 16 years later and
we're still in Afghanistan. One of the
interesting things about that is that
whether it was from a public relations
perspective or whether or not it was was
actual fact, the perception of what the
CI CIA accomplished in Afghanistan was
very positive. And yet, if one looks at
the history of of CIA operations, there
certainly is not a great record of
success.
There really is not a great record of
success. You can go all the way back to
the creation, the foundation of the CIA
in in 1947 with the passage of the
National Security Act and look at um
covert action programs that have been
declassified since 1947. And uh I'm I'm
hardressed to find a success. talk a
little bit about it in the context of
really the original mission of the CIA,
which was really pretty much analytical
and intelligence gathering. That's
right. The I I say this all the time. It
It's actually quite simple what the CIA
is supposed to do. The CIA is supposed
to recruit spies to steal secrets and
then analyze those secrets to pass the
analysis to policymakers so that they
can make the best informed policy. And
now that's actually very little of what
the CIA does. Now there are these
paramilitary units that are parachuting
or helicoptering into remote locations
to kill people or to kidnap people. Uh
we know just recently from Wikileaks
that there's now this huge uh cyber
espionage uh uh directorate or division,
whatever it is, uh that's that's
targeting the iPhone and and the Android
phone and the Samsung smart TV and and
even our cars, the computers in our
cars. That's not the CIA that I joined
and I don't think that's the CIA that
Congress had in mind when it created the
organization. How much was this and all
of this activity the creation of the CIA
itself and how much was molded by
whatever administration was in
power? Well, I I think that the CIA
really wasn't
necessarily molded administration to
administration except for a couple of
exceptions. Uh the CIA went a little
well the CIA went a lot over the top
during the Johnson administration let's
say um but more in more modern times
um I have to be careful how I say this
because I don't want to put point too
many fingers and get myself in trouble
again. I I'll say it this way. In in my
lifetime in my career the CIA was really
not a political or politicized
organization. I had no idea the
political affiliation or inclinations of
of the people sitting next to me or the
people I worked for. Politics never came
up. It was never discussed. I remember
one time uh in 1996 a woman in my office
got in trouble because she had a Bob
Dole bumper sticker on her desk. She was
ordered to remove it. Uh and so politics
just never played a role in day-to-day
life at the CIA until September 11th.
And then it became very political and
very politicized. It was actually worse
under the Obama administration than it
was under the George W. Bush
administration. And I think that that's
really the genesis of this fight that
we're now seeing between the CIA and the
Trump White House. How did it become
more politicized specifically during the
Obama years?
Obama was very good at cultivating
people inside the CIA. You know, one of
the things that's funny to me is the CIA
prides itself on its ability to recruit
uh and I I use that in quotes to recruit
new presidents. What they do is
especially when a president really has
little or no national security
background or experience like Barack
Obama, they start briefing him as soon
as he's elected president. And I can
tell you as soon as that new president
sees his first blue border report or
black border report, something that's so
highly classified it has to have a blank
cover page. It's classified at a level
several several levels above top secret.
That's heady stuff. And then they do the
briefing and they say, "Mr.
President-elect, we want to tell you
about all the cool things we're doing
around the world." Well, once they've
let that president in on all the
secrets, they've recruited him and he's
one of the guys. He's a part of the
club. They did that with Barack Obama.
But Obama was smart, too. And Obama
began sending people to the CIA that he
knew were political loyalists. You know,
John Brennan was one. John Brennan was
supposed to be the first CIA director uh
under Obama, but progressives objected.
Don't forget that John Brennan was the
number three at the CIA under George W.
Bush and was up to his neck in the
torture program even though he denied it
later. Uh there was nothing progressive
about John Brennan. So Obama knew he
could wait out the liberals and that's
exactly what he did. Uh as soon as he
won re-election, he named John Brennan
CIA director and nobody objected by
then. At the same time, Brennan brought
his own people in and they too were
Obama loyalists. they had owed their
careers to Obama. The next thing you
know, you have this politicized
leadership at the CIA when the CIA is
supposed to be nonpartisan, apolitical.
Um, and frankly, I don't think we saw
that kind of politization of the agency
since the Reagan administration when
when U. Casey brought in businessmen,
Wall Street friends of his to be the
deputy director and deputy director for
operations. To what extent then is the
CIA shaped by and and each
administration differently shaped by the
impact of of the president and the
director that he appoints? It normally
shouldn't be but uh but it is now. See
the the president will appoint a
director and a deputy director. the
deputy director is almost always either
a career officer or a military officer
because and again, especially since
September 11th, there are these military
programs and and military and
paramilitary offices. So, it's it's
probably wise to have somebody with
military experience to advise you. And
it's my experience that it's the
military guys, it's the generals who are
the least likely to use military force
because they know how terrible war can
be. Um but that's that's changed now.
Now you have presidents like Obama
appointing the the director the deputy
director and then appointing the
divisional deputy directors the deputy
director for operations for for uh
intelligence which is analysis for
science and technology. um and and it
becomes more political than at a lower
level that is going to eventually
trickle down and the end result
unfortunately is going to be the
politization of analysis which is very
difficult or I'm sorry which is very
which is a very bad thing. Um and let me
add one more thing about the
politization of intelligence. One of the
golden rules at the CIA when I was an
analyst was that you could never ever
make a policy recommendation, right? We
were not a policy-making organization.
We were an intelligence gathering and
analysis organization. And so your job
was to give the president the news, put
it into context so he can make a policy
decision. George W. Bush changed that
and mandated that every article that ran
in the president's daily brief had to
also have a policy recommendation
paragraph. That was a very dangerous
development and it it insinuated the CIA
into the policym process which should
have been the domain of just the white
house and the state department. And did
those recommendations continue during
the Obama years? they did in the
beginning uh through Obama's first uh
term and it's my understanding that
they've finally gone by the wayside but
in the meantime you have all these Obama
loyalists that are there and so the
effect I think is the same and which
brings us to to the present situation
and what the impact is today. One of the
things that has been kind of amusing to
me about this whole fight between Trump
and the CIA is I think most Americans
have consistently underestimated Donald
Trump. We we think he's a buffoon. We
think he's insane. We think he's
short-tempered. And in fact, he probably
has had a longer term view and and he
fooled a lot of us. Well, I think that
Donald Trump has underestimated the CIA.
You know, the CIA has worked for
presidents who didn't like it in the
past. Bill Clinton was no fan of the
CIA. Jimmy Carter certainly was no fan
of the CIA. And John Kennedy was
legendary. John Kennedy wanted to break
up the CIA into a million pieces. It's a
shame he didn't have the opportunity to
do it. Um, and I think Donald Trump
thought that he could just snap his
fingers and and point and people would
fall into line. That's just not the way
the CIA works. you know, the at the
working level, most CIA officers when
once you get up to a position of, let's
say, GS-15 or higher, you get into the
senior intelligence service, you've been
there for 20, 25, 30 years, and you
know, you can wait out this president.
You know, this guy's only going to be
around for four years or 8 years. And uh
you've weeded out other presidents in
the past. And I think that's exactly
what what the CIA is doing now. They
know that Trump's not going to be around
forever and they will be around forever
and they're just going to wait him out.
Some of it though is goes beyond waiting
out. Some of it is really pushing back.
A lot of it is pushing back. You know,
there are several things besides just
waiting that the CIA can do. The CIA can
elect to, for example, not carry out
covert action programs um ordered by the
president. they can just say that it's
not possible or that it's too dangerous
or it they just don't have the manpower
for it. And so if the president wants to
enact a certain policy, the CIA can
essentially just say no, they're not
going to do that. Um I've seen that
happen in the past. U the CIA can also
elect to not target uh uh the top spy
prospects. Um they and they can do that
to try to embarrass the president. Let's
say you need a you need a a source
inside XYZ terrorist group. You know,
why take the risk? It's just going to
make the president look good. And so,
you don't do that. And then, you know,
when there's another attack, god forbid,
it's on this president's watch and the
buck has to stop there. You predicted
that the CIA was going to have some
influence and play some kind of a role
behind the scenes in getting rid of
Michael Flynn. Talk about that. I did.
Um, I'm actually impressed that you uh
that you know that um Michael Flynn was
one of the most wildly unpopular people
uh that I've ever encountered uh in the
intelligence community. He didn't like
the CIA. The CIA didn't like him. They
didn't trust him. Uh he was the director
of the Defense Intelligence Agency,
which is sort of seen as the the poor
the poor second cousin of the CIA. Uh
there there used to be a kind of a a
mean-spirited joke that the only people
who worked at DIA were people who
couldn't make it through the CIA hiring
process. And so there was always this
animosity between Flynn and um and the
agency. And then all of a sudden, with
the stroke of a pen, after Donald Trump
is elected president, uh, Flynn is named
national security adviser, which gives
him primacy over the CIA. The CIA was
not going to allow that to happen. And I
can't help but to think that so many of
these leaks that we're hearing about,
you know, coordination with the Russians
or whatever the leaks are, I can't help
but think that they aren't coming out of
the CIA.
And to what extent do you think the CIA
was involved in this whole dossier that
that Clapper presented to the president
and all the things surrounding that?
Yeah. That had CIA written all over it.
The the British officer who compiled the
dossier um Christopher Steele uh is an
MI6 officer. MI6 is the is the sister
organization the the liison organization
of the CIA. It's MI6 that CIA normally
deals with just like FBI normally deals
with both MI5 in the UK and Scotland
Yard. So no MI6 officer, past or
present, would initiate such a such a
dossier, such an investigation without
the direct input of the CIA. I I think
that the CIA's fingerprints were all
over that whole operation. And and
Christopher Steel, who you knew, talk a
little bit about what what his
involvement might have been. Yeah, I I
actually worked with Christopher Steele
nearly 20 years ago on Greek terrorism
after the assassination of the British
defense ates in Athens. I found I found
him to be an absolutely outstanding
officer, smart, suave, analytic,
accomplished, truly good at his job. So,
whoever hired him to do this
investigation and to compile this
dossier knew exactly the kind of person
that they needed to carry this out and
they knew to go to the best. Well, who
would know such a thing other than the
CIA because they they had worked with
him for many many years. What do you
make of these uh Wikileaks documents
that came out yesterday about the CIA's
hacking efforts?
I I spent most of the day going through
these documents and although they were
they were written certainly many years
after I left the agency, they they
appear to me to be legitimate uh uh
documents, CIA documents. Um I'm worried
most about the CIA spying on American
citizens. It it made me just sick to my
stomach to see that the CIA had cracked
the iPhone. They had cracked the Google
Android. They had cracked the Samsung
smart TV and apparently had even cracked
the uh the computers that are in our
cars now that that should sometime in
the near future allow us to uh to have
um automated driving.
Uh look, I I want I want a robust
intelligence service in this country to
protect American citizens. I want an
intelligence service that we can trust
and that we can have confidence in. Uh,
I don't want to have to worry about my
intelligence service spying on me or on
other American citizens. That's
unconstitutional. It's illegal and it's
not something Americans should have to
worry about, unfortunately, because
there is literally no congressional
oversight of the CIA. That's exactly
what we have to worry about. We have to
worry about the CIA spying on us. What
do we know about Mike Pompeo and what we
might expect from him?
Well, I have a I have a very close
friend who uh has briefed Mike Pompeo
more than a dozen times, and this was
before Pompeo became the CIA director.
And he said to me, "Pompeo's domestic
politics aside,
uh this is actually a very bright guy.
This is a guy with no real political
ties to Donald Trump. It's a guy who's a
patriot and uh who wants to do the right
thing with the agency." That made me
happy until he named Gina Haspel as the
CIA's deputy director. Uh I I don't like
Mike Pompeo's domestic politics, but
again, his position on abortion, for
example, has nothing to do with his
ability to lead the CIA. I'm perfectly
happy to put that aside. It's my
understanding that he's an excellent
manager and that he's a good leader, but
I think that he just doesn't understand.
for example, that something like torture
is patently illegal in this country and
it's not something that we should be
pursuing. So, I think the jury is still
out over the long term. Which brings us
around to your situation. And for our
listeners that don't know, talk a little
bit about what you went through.
Well, when I returned from Pakistan uh
in 2002, I should add in Pakistan, I led
a series of raids that resulted in the
capture of Abu Zuba and many dozens of
al-Qaeda fighters. I'm not allowed to
say the exact number. Um, we believed at
the time that Abu Zuba was the number
three in al-Qaeda. That turned out to
not be true. Although he was a bad guy,
he had never actually joined al-Qaeda.
So, I got back to headquarters in the
middle of 2002 and was asked by a senior
officer in the counterterrorism center
if I wanted to be what he called
certified in the use of enhanced
interrogation techniques. Uh, I had
never heard that term before and I asked
him what he meant and he described to me
um these 10 techniques and I said that
sounds like a torture program. I don't
think I want to be a part of that. But I
said give me an hour. Let me think about
it. And in that hour, I went up to the
CIA's seventh floor, the executive
floor, and uh consulted with a very
senior CIA officer for whom I had worked
in the Middle East a decade earlier. And
I said, "What do you think about this?"
And he said, "First, let's call it what
it is. It's a torture program. They can
use whatever euphemism they want, but
this is a torture program. Second,
torture is a slippery slope, and you
know how these guys are, my colleagues."
He said, "Somebody's going to go
overboard and they're going to kill a
prisoner and then there's going to be a
congressional investigation and then
there's going to be a Justice Department
investigation and somebody's going to go
to prison. Do you want to go to prison?"
I said, "No, I don't want to go to
prison." And ironically, I'm the only
one who went to prison. But I said,
"No." And I went back downstairs and I
told the CTC officer, "This is a torture
program and I don't want any part of
it." Well, that was in May of 2002. On
August 1st, 2002, the CIA began to
torture Abu Zuba. And this torture was
merciless. We've made a lot about
waterboarding and what a terrible uh
torture technique waterboarding is. But
there were things that were worse than
waterboarding in my view. Things like
sleep deprivation. You know, people
begin to lose their their minds around
day seven of of sleep deprivation and
they begin to die at day nine. But the
CIA was authorized to keep people awake
as long as 12 days. Um, indeed, there's
one Guantanamo defendant who's unable to
participate in his own defense because
he lost his mind through the use of
sleep deprivation. Another technique was
called the cold cell where a prisoner is
stripped naked and he's chained to an
eyebolt in the ceiling. So, he can't
kneel or sit. He can't get into any
comfortable position. The cell is
chilled to 50° F and then every hour
someone goes in and throws a bucket of
ice water on him. We killed people using
that technique. But the torturers were
never prosecuted. The the people who
went overboard and who killed the
prisoners were never prosecuted. The the
CIA CIA officer who destroyed taped
evidence of the torture was never
prosecuted. the lawyers who came up with
it, you know, who who used specious
legal arguments to justify it, the pro
the uh psychologists who who invented
it, no, nobody was ever prosecuted. In
fact, we have very specific laws in this
country. We have the 1946 torture act
which specifically outlawed the
techniques that we used against
prisoners post 911.
And the United States is not just a
signatory but was the drafter of the
international convention against torture
uh which has primacy over US law. Uh
both of those laws outlawed torture. And
I'll add one more thing. In
1946, the US government executed
Japanese soldiers who had waterboarded
American prisoners of war. That was an
executable offense in
1946. And in January of
1968, the Washington Post ran a front
page photograph of an American soldier
waterboarding a North Vietnamese
prisoner. That soldier, that American
was prosecuted. He was convicted of
torture and he was sentenced to 20 years
in a military prison. Well, the law
never changed between 1946 and
now. So all I conclude is that we
changed and we decided that this was the
kind of people that we wanted to be to
allow this kind of of abomination as
part of our policy. Well, I decided in
in 2007 after keeping my mouth shut for
a long time that uh that I would go
public and that's what I did in an
interview with ABC News. And were you
the only one? Were there others that
felt as you did that didn't come forward
or were there others that just went
along? To tell you the truth, in 2002,
um I was the only one 14 of us were
asked if we wanted to be trained in
these torture techniques and I was the
only one who said no. I there was this
feeling of of vengeance. You know, we we
were still so traumatized by 9/11 that
people wanted revenge on on al-Qaeda. Uh
but we know now from the Senate torture
report primarily that there were people
who were objecting internally. Uh a
couple of them even cretailed their
their assignments at the secret prison
where Abu Zubedo was being tortured and
they went back to headquarters which is
a careerending decision but nobody ever
went public. Even after the Senate
torture report was released nobody went
public. John Keryaku thank you so much
for spending time with us here on radio.
Who? What? Why? Thanks for having me. It
was a pleasure. Thank you. Thank you for
listening and joining us here on Radio
Who Why. I hope you join us next week
for another Radio Who Why podcast. I'm
Jeff Sheckchman. If you like this
podcast, please feel free to share and
help others find it by rating and
reviewing it on iTunes. You can also
support this podcast and all the work we
do by going to whoy.org/donate.